Chester J. Higman papers, 1957-1984
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Chester J. Higman papers, 1957-1984
MS 292
Higman, Chester J., d1910-
This collection is comprised of council minutes, development programs, journals, mining and mineral rights, range ordinances, correspondence, and background materials that document Higman's efforts to assist the Tribal Council in improving conditions. Among the correspondence is material relating to the U. S. Army Corps of Engineers' construction of the Painted Rocks Reservoir.
1.5 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
A graduate of the University of Washington, Chester Higman worked in a variety of businesses in the United States, and served as a volunteer for the American Friends Service Committee in Mexico prior to 1958.
As the first Administrative Assistant employed by the Tribal Council, Higman was involved in all aspects of tribal affairs. His chief duties included advising the Chairman and Council, drafting resolutions and ordinances, compiling Council minutes, managing business affairs of the reservation and personnel in the Tribal Office, and directing public relations. He resigned his position in June 1961.
Scope and Content Note
The collection best documents Higman's efforts to assist the Tribal Council in improving their internal communications and policies, and in consolidating their endeavors to improve economic conditions on the reservation.
The larger files include Council Minutes, Development Programs, Journals, Mining and Mineral Rights, and Range Ordinances. Of interest are his reflections on daily developments in administration of the office in the Journals, and his evaluations and suggestions for restructuring in Recommendations for Improvements.
Most of the files contain both correspondence and background materials relating the specific topic; some folders contain items that predate Higman's tenure but relate to the topic. For example, the Districts file contains letters about the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers' construction of the Painted Rocks Reservoir, and articles of incorporation for the East Chuichu Project and the San Xavier Non-Profit Development Company.
Access Terms
Higman, Chester J., 1910- -- Archives
Tohono O'Odham Tribal Council
Tohono O'Odham Indians -- Politics and government
Indian reservations -- Arizona
Papago Indian Reservation (Ariz.)
Painted Rocks Reservoir (Ariz.) -- History
Minutes
Journals
Correspondence
Container List
- Administrative Assistant: miscellaneous. 1957-1963 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Allotted Lands. ca. 1960 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- American Friends Service Committee. 1957-1959 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Bureau of Indian Affairs: reorganization and relationship to tribal organizations. 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Commissioner of Indian Affairs Conference, El Paso. 1956 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence: general. 1951-1961, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
- Development Program Proposals: economic and social. 1950-1961 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Districts: Chuichu, Gila Bend, Painted Rocks, San Xavier, Sells, Sif Oidak. 1953-1961 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Education. 1959-1961 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Financial. 1949-1961 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Government: Tribal Council Constitution and Bylaws; Minutes. 1931, 1951-1958 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Government: Minutes. 1959 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Government: Minutes. 1960 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Government: Minutes. 1961 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Government: Ordinances, Nos. 1-36. 1937-1958 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- History, Maps and Statistics. ca. 1960 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Indians: citizenship and political participation. 1957-1959 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Journals. 1958-1960 (Box 2, Folder 6-8)
- Labor Relations. 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Land Claim. 1958-1959 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Law and Order. Includes draft of law code. 1957-1960 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Leases: agricultural, commercial, mining. 1957-1960 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Mining and Mineral Rights. 1956-1961 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Other Arizona Indians: Hopi, Navajo, Salt River Pima Maricopa. 1960-1962 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Range Ordinances and Range Water Development. 1958-1961 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Recommendations for Improvements. 1959-1961 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Religion. 1956-1961 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Telephone System. 1960 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Tribal Business Management Conference, Phoenix. 1959 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Tribal Herd and Miscellaneous enterprises. 1959-1961 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Miscellaneous Printed Materials. 1949-1961 (Box 3, Folder 9)